I'm not going to I'm just making a face
like I can't hack for less than 3 hours.
Are you serious? Are you freaking
kidding me right now, dude? Like you
telling me that you never you very
rarely hack for longer than 3 hour
contiguous periods? Yeah, that's Yeah,
that's pretty
Oh my god, how do you even hack? Oh my
gosh.
My eyes hurt, man.
What's up, y'all? Before we hop into
this episode today, I just wanted to
give a little bit of an introduction.
We were graced by the magnificent
presence of Mr. Douglas Day, aka
Archangel, on the episode today.
Joel and I know Douglas from the live
hacking event community where we have
competed against him and collaborated
with him
many times. So, it was a pleasure to
have him on the pod. Douglas is known
for a couple things in the live hacking
event community, the primary of which is
his collaboration abilities. Douglas
almost always collaborates with other
hackers on the live hacking event scene,
and he has taken home nine best
collaboration awards over his time at
the live hacking events. So, a very
impressive number. He's also known
specifically for his volume of reports
that he submits. He finds a lot of bugs
and has a really dialed-in radar for
what is a bug and what's not a bug to a
company.
And he also has a lot of I guess he has
a very methodical approach to bug
bounty. He has a lot of methods,
techniques that he uses
that work really well for him and get
good results. So, for those of you that
are a little bit more method-oriented, I
think this will be a great episode for
you.
All right, I think that's it. So,
without further ado, enjoy the episode.
Boom, we're rolling. Douglas, welcome to
the pod, man. Thanks, good to be here.
So, I guess we'll start out today. We
got to got to warm up got to warm up our
our podcasting voices, our podcasting
element. I'm working on my radio voice.
Yeah,
this guy's got it already. Let's let's
let's start off. Why don't you tell us a
little bit about how you got into
infosec and how you got eventually you
got into bug bounties? Cuz right now
you're you're on the program side as
well as on the hacker side, right? Yeah,
more or less, yeah. I
I spend less time on the program side
these days.
However, I am associated with a
with the Elastic program. So, although
I'm I'm less and less active as the as
the days go on. Is your role just
shifting with that or is it
Yeah, yeah, I do I do a lot more
infrastructure side security. So,
working on like Terraform, Kubernetes,
um
sort of running our infosec
infrastructure and I
passed on the the bug bounty to our
product security team. So, but we can
get into that
a little later.
Yeah, so so tell me about how you landed
this this position at at Elastic and
work back in your infosec history. Yeah,
I'll work backwards. That's probably a
good way to go. So, uh back in 2020, I
was the number one hacker on the Elastic
bug bounty program. It was a very small
program then. I think we were offering
like 1K credits
and for a very complicated tech stack
like Elastic, that's pretty suboptimal.
But I was the number one hacker
nonetheless
and then around
the turn of the turn of the new year,
they were looking for someone to run the
bug bounty program and they thought, why
not take our number one hacker and have
him build up the program. So, I applied,
threw my hat to the
to the application process and and
landed the job and then built out the
built out the bug bounty program over at
Elastic. Launched about 2 years later.
Um And I think we had like the sixth
most active bug bounty launch on the
HackerOne platform. Oh, nice.
So, yeah, we saw a we had a very very
wide scope to start and so we saw a lot
of submissions. Um
But yeah, it was a it was a pretty
successful launch. But they moved me
backwards.
This was goodness. This was 2020, like
the the dawn of 2020 and I started my
bug bounty career.
The year of the year of darkness, the
the year that everything changed. Right,
I know, right? But so I but I started
bug bounty about 2 years before that in
October of
or I guess about a year and a half
before that in October of 2018. I'd gone
to um
I'd gone to BSides Portland in which Ben
Sadeghipour and the Homsec was running a
a uh
uh what do you call it? A presentation
at at BSides and I was like, oh hey,
that looks that's looks pretty fun. I
started my HackerOne account um
that evening and I got my first bounty
about 2 months later. Dude, so so Ben is
Ben is a part of your origin story, huh?
Yeah, yeah, he he he is.
right off the bat at that at that at
that conference and that's how you
weaseled your way into bug bounty? Yeah,
yeah, and so it was kind of a it was
pretty slow slow at the start. I didn't
expect to be part of like the the
community like I am today. I didn't
expect to ever be participating in live
events. But about a year after I started
I created my account, I remember getting
my very first live hacking event invite.
I was I was at the gym. I was about to
start a workout in the morning over at
24 Hour Fitness and I get like an email.
It's like And this is like this is like
mid-July and so like the
uh
I I was definitely a last-minute
addition. Like I didn't I didn't try to
get an invite or anything. I think
somebody dropped and so I got a 702
invite for uh for 2019's
for the 2019 Vegas and I was like, oh,
what is this? You know, what is what is
the live hacking event? What is the dupe
window? I don't know.
So, I I showed up and I remember like I
was talking to you. I show up and not
knowing what to expect on very first
live event. I think I
I mistakenly didn't realize the value of
the dupe window and so I spent maybe
like 2 hours in the dupe window hacking
and then thought I'd do all my
Yeah, I thought I'd do all my hacking at
the Yeah, at the at the event as well.
So, for for those of you that aren't
familiar with live hacking event
structure, so typically how it works,
there's a before the live hacking event,
there is a window, you know, normally
something like a week and a half, 2
weeks maybe sometimes, of
period where you can where everyone's
hacking on the target, everyone knows
the scope, everyone knows the policy,
everything like that. But during that
period, if you find any bugs that anyone
else has has found and you submit them,
then those dupes get split. So, what
Douglas is saying here is that he didn't
hack at all during this period where he
was supposed to be hacking and prepping
and because of that he probably lost
himself the opportunity to get in on a
bunch of bugs that he would have
otherwise found and split those, you
know, some of those low-hanging fruits
that other other hackers will find get
split the bounties on those. Is that
Does that
Did I summarize that well enough?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's pretty that's
pretty accurate. So, I came into the
dupe window with like one event and I
remember I remember showing up to the to
the welcome party. I think it was at
Topgolf that year and um
Dude, no. That was I missed I wanted to
go to that so bad.
I was flying in and I was on the plane
and then a like a sandstorm hit and it
had to defer to a different airport and
I missed your first live hacking event,
you know.
Sandstorm.
I was so sad, man.
but so but so I'm there and I'm like
talking with other people. I have no
idea who these who these people are by
their face. I think like
I think like Pierre Lucas, you know, a
Ram sexy like came up to me and he's
like so so who are you? And you know, I
didn't know who I was and he like looked
at my profile and he
and he even asked he's like, so how did
you get invited to this? No. I I
Not not that not that it doesn't mean he
was being mean or anything, but like I
I wasn't the plus one. I didn't know I
didn't know anybody else and I was kind
of like a a nobody like hacker. I was
kind of a I don't I have no idea how I
got invited. I was just like a like a
random last-minute addition and so I I
knew no one. Um but I I had a had a
great time at the event, learned, okay,
you actually use the dupe window to
hack, but
most importantly, I made a couple of
good connections uh who then plus one to
me to the Los Angeles event a couple
months later and then after that I've
sort of been on the been on the live
event train for the last 4 years or 3
years or 4 years, yeah. Yeah, man, it's
it's a ride, man. It really is.
So, I mean, you you got you went to that
Los Angeles live hacking event and is
that when the sort of collaboration
train started? You know, from from those
connections you made and then you
started collaborating every single event
cuz that's I mean, that's your go-to MO
now, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. So, so I was
a plus one um and give you know, given
this is my second So, the LA event was
my very second event. I was still wasn't
exactly sure how they were supposed to
work. Um and so I I was Hogarth45's plus
one to that event. Um
yeah, I was like
hey, I since I'm a plus one, I assumed
that since I was his plus one, we'd have
to team up and so and he was he was
chill with it and then uh
I don't remember why, but we wanted to
have like a a more like a bigger team
and so I think we grabbed we grabbed Ram
sexy and we grabbed Mr. TuxRacer uh for
our for our team. Yeah, yeah, yeah. And
so we just kind of went ham. I think it
was Air Force that time. Um
Uh it was yeah, Air Force and Verizon
Media and we just went went ham on them
and we were we were we were a bit salty
because this was before the best
collaboration award was a thing. I think
they started it like the following event
or the event after. And so we like
obliterated as a team um
and would have would have gotten the the
best team award at that
award existed at the time. But but no,
it was a it was a it was a great event.
We
you know, we we did really well and then
subsequent events I've just kind of
gotten invited uh
uh over and over again, fortunately.
And um yeah, I had such a fun time um
just kind of collabing uh
during the during the live event this
time.
Uh you know, hopping on video calls, uh
sharing ideas, just kind of hanging out,
talking about life or whatever with with
the guys. And uh I've just kind of
haven't haven't gone back. Uh that's
kind of how I've done most
most subsequent events. I have a number
of events like one or two where I wasn't
really I didn't
I think like some of the virtual ones
where I didn't I didn't collab as much.
Um but for for every event that I've
been to in person, I've I've for sure
tried to tried to team up with with one
to
four other hackers, I suppose.
Yeah, I think it's always it's really
interesting to see how collabing has
changed over the years in live hacking
events. I think in the beginning like
there was very little collaboration that
was done and it was very like
only like tightly knit groups of people
or like people who like were used to
hacking with each other and now I feel
like
everybody collabs with everybody. Like
there's a lot more knowledge sharing and
a lot more like open collaboration that
kind of stuff nowadays. Um
There there is, yeah.
Yeah, when So when you're collaborating,
would you say it's mostly like the same
people or do you split it up or
I think say more more or less the same
people. I guess I just like collabing
with people that I that I know and that
I'm that I'm already friends with. Uh
every once in a while I call want to
collab with someone that they'll also
want to collab with someone else and so
we'll bring that man in and
you know, that person becomes a becomes
a friend of mine. But I've got a number
of regulars like uh all the all the
French Canadians, almost all the French
Canadians I've collabed with. Like I've
collabed with DC, I've collabed with uh
Pier-Luc, I've collabed with uh
Sebastian, I collabed with uh uh J Rock
17 now. Um
So a bunch of French Canadians I
collabed with Alex Chapman a lot. I
collabed with Rez0 a lot. Um Space
Racoon.
Um
Corvex even. Um so there's been a a
number of
a number of uh hackers that I've I've
kind of worked Oh, Today is new has been
a been a common a common thread. Um
Hussein. I mean, I could go on and on
the more more I think about it. Well, at
the at the most recent live hacking
events, I've kind of seen you with the
group with of Rez0 and and Alex Chapman.
Mhm. And uh and that that seems to be a
pretty a pretty functional group that
you guys have have held across a couple
live hacking events. And I've I noticed,
you know, one of the one of the main
problems that I have with collaboration
because um both both um Joel and I uh
were a part of Disturbunce, right? Which
was a uh
giant hacking team uh that we had going
on for a little while. But um you know,
kind of the ways that the way that we
saw that or the way that it it worked
worked out was, you know, there was so
much variation in how everyone would
perform at the live hacking events,
right? So if you
if you if you performed well and then
you were then you were losing money a
lot of the time, right? But if you
performed poorly, you were feeling like
you were dragging your friends down,
right? So the only times that it you
know, so those are both both negative
outcomes for for me. This is this is why
I rarely collab at live hacking events
anymore beyond, you know, or at least
not full split collabs. Um and and in
the only scenario when it really works
out well if for for me is when we both
add equal value and it just kind of
edges out and you know, we both have
have fun with it, right? Um and and Joel
and I were able to pull that off live
hacking event uh you know, earlier this
year um and that was great. But um so my
question to you is like, how do you deal
with the that up and down of
collaboration and how do you how do you
communicate with your your long-term
collaboration partners to make that
work?
Yeah, so I should preface this by saying
I've been to a lot of events. I think
that if if a live event was something
that I knew it was going only going to
happen once, then I'd have a lot more to
lose.
Um but goodness, after 15 live events,
I've been the the under contributor on
some, I've been the over contributor on
some and there have been some where it's
been kind of been kind of in the middle.
Um and I think that the the sting of
under contributing and the sting of
losing money because you were an over
contributor
they they both sting less than the sting
of showing up to an event by yourself
empty-handed. And so I think Yeah. I
think uh
collabing and guaranteeing
like decent success because you've
you've got a solid team, even if you
might under contribute and feel like a
uh you know, a bozo or you over
contribute and feel like you lost some
money.
Um in the end it's basically
guaranteeing you know, it it's it's I
guess uh hedging your risks. It's uh
you know, kind of like diversifying your
your bug bounty portfolio in a way. Um
and so over the course of many events, I
think it it kind of averages out. If you
have a if you have somebody who's like
consistently underachieving whether
because they
they maybe aren't up to skill with live
hacking events or are
just not uh trying, then you can kind of
like start to seed those out over the
course of time. But I don't know. Like
the the amount of fun I have with with
bug bounty events and the the value I
get just being a part of the community
is is worth the you know, couple of live
events where maybe I I lose like, you
know,
a few thousand dollars due to just over
contributing. It's like And
I think another part of it is it's
really really hard to uh
Yeah, it it it's really hard to quantify
the value like the
it's really hard to quantify the value
that collaboration brings. Cuz there's
been a number of times where I've been
collabing with someone who didn't submit
who themselves didn't submit a lot of
bugs.
But I all of my bugs were because of a
something that they that they sent in
Discord or or Slack or whatever. You
know, maybe they were like looking maybe
they were looking at some domain that I
didn't realize was in scope. And then
because they were looking at that
domain, I found a link to another domain
which was super vulnerable and I
submitted tons of bugs on that. And it's
like, okay, I'm the one that's that
found all these bugs, but would I have
found it? I don't know. Uh and so it's
it's really hard to quantify like how
much just being a part of the of the
collaboration process uh
adds to the adds to the team. And so
maybe maybe I'll figure out a way to to
add a dollar value to it, but I haven't
reached that point yet.
Yeah, I've I've I've really noticed that
a lot with like So when when events
first went virtual um after in in
person, it was very difficult I feel
like at least for me to like try and get
that sense of like collaboration that
you get at events. And I think a lot of
it boils down to what you were talking
about there where it's not so much like
that person submitted so many bugs or
whatever. It's that the combined
brainpower of the people in the room is
working towards like a singular goal.
And so if you have five people looking
at the same thing, there's so much so
many more minds and threads thinking
about that bug and how to be creative
with it Mhm. at the same time that make
it so much easier to find impactful
vulnerabilities when you're working as a
group.
Um
Absolutely.
And there's not an easy way to like
measure that, right? Like you said, like
just because they didn't submit a
vulnerability doesn't mean that they
didn't contribute significantly to that
vulnerability just if, you know, they're
a collaborator on it or whatever. That
that doesn't really get accounted for
super well. Um and so I think like that
whole aspect of it is very interesting.
I'm curious especially it seems like a
lot of the people you work with are not
people who are local to you. So are
there certain things that you do when
you're collaborating to help aid with
that collaboration? I know for Justin
and I it was very very helpful for us to
basically just be in a call all day like
all day every day while we were hacking
together. 12-hour 12-hour Discord call.
Yeah, and that basically like created
sort of that same environment where
you're like next to each other kind of.
You're all looking you're like both
looking at the same thing. You're, you
know, both your minds are working on the
same thing together. That that type of
stuff. Do you have any tricks that you
use?
Yeah, so I I also do video calls. I do
video calls or audio calls. And it's
it's so nice just to
um
set one up even if you're not talking
that whole time just to be like, oh,
wait, I think I found something and then
the other person kind of sidetrack what
they're working on and help you just
decide whether or not it's a it's like a
true positive or a false positive.
Sometimes it's not and you just go back
to working. But just having having that
sort of desk buddy um just on the other
side of the screen is is super super
helpful. Um
that's been that's been where we've
found some of our some of our coolest
our coolest bugs when we were just uh
working together uh on a Zoom call and
then someone found something that was
interesting and then we all just kind of
dogpiled on it and then boom. Uh
So I I think I'm I may sound a little
bit like a negative Nancy with
collaboration. Like I love
collaboration, I really do. But here's
the other thing with that, right? Like I
I don't always mean to be bringing up
the cons, but here you know, I I got to
do it. So like in the situations, Joel
and I um we were pair hacking pretty
much uh during this live hacking event
by the nature of what the target was and
the way we were doing it. So we we it
wasn't the two of us going down and and
looking at you know, different routes
and and that sort of thing and then
comparing notes. It was both of us
looking at one screen saying, okay, what
if we did this? What if we did that? You
know, that sort of thing. And it worked
out great. The but in the past I've done
the route that you guys sort of just
described of like both on a video call,
working on your own things and then
pulling people in when you need them.
And it really I guess it just depends on
the person, right? But like sometimes
you get that person that's like, hey,
look at this every like five minutes,
right? And it's like like I can't think
because I I as soon as I get in my flow
state, you know, it's I I can't you
know,
I get pulled out and pulled into
something else. So I feel like I'm I'm
more becoming like a a support hacker
rather than you know, somebody who's
trying to find his own his own bug. So,
I mean, I guess
I don't know if I want to put you on the
spot and say like, have you ever
experienced that with, you know, the
people you've collaborated with? But,
what what what's your thoughts on the
way we could deal with that
collaboration little mishap?
Yeah, so it I mean, it does happen to
me. I think I um
I don't think either way is is wrong or
right. I think that I've I've been in
There have been times where I've been
like in a flow state and like maybe like
Rez0 has been been just kind of like
taking a more like wide scope and be
like, "Oh, this thing's interesting."
And you know, just slaps in a like a
fuzz or a fuzz result into Discord, you
know, something that's not even an
application, but might look interesting
and I'll be like, "Okay, I'll I'll I'll
just have to be like, okay, I'm going
to, you know, mute I'm going to hop off
the call for
for 20 minutes, 30 minutes, whatever
while I while I dig into this." Or and
he he I guess we've we've worked
together enough that he can kind of know
when I'm in a like I'm I'm focused on a
on a bug and uh
maybe maybe it's just kind of having
that having that relationship where
he doesn't take offense if I'm like,
"Okay, I'm I'm I need to focus on this."
Um
and then he'll he'll usually be like,
"Yeah, yeah, yeah, you you you focus on
that. I'll I'll I'll dig it I'll dig
deeper." And I don't know. Yeah, hasn't
I I could see it I could see it being
coming like a a problem if I was working
with someone I hadn't worked with before
and I didn't have that rapport and
respect to be able to kindly, but
but uh reasonably be like, "I need to I
need to focus for for a few minutes." It
sounds like good It sounds like good
bound boundaries, you know, in hacking,
right? You know, you're saying, "Okay,
you know what? At the end of the day,
I think this is counterproductive right
now. So, I'm going to say, 'Hey, I'm
going to mute this channel for 5
minutes, you know, while everyone's
doing the recon dump or or I'm going to
hop off this call and just like put on
some, you know, whatever alpha neural
beats or whatever those are that like
makes your brain go into focus mode."
And that's sort of thing. Um
And then, you know, you can you can make
it happen as long as you're
communicating well with your with your
collaborator. So, I don't know, man.
Maybe I just wasn't Maybe I just wasn't,
you know, my communication game wasn't
on fleek in the past.
Well, I
again, I don't think there's a I don't
think there's a right and a wrong way to
do it. I'm actually entertaining the
idea of trying the next several events
just solo to see to see what I can do
cuz I think there's there's several ways
to do collab. There's the collab that
that I do and that I usually do which is
just, you know, full-on team collab,
split everything, we're just going to
act as a act as a unit. Um but then
there's uh people like um like I think
the the the way you sort of do collab
and the way like Nagli might do collab
is, you know, go solo and then if you if
you need help on a specific thing, pull
in somebody.
Um and that's that's potentially a way
to go. There's also hackers like um
I can't think of anybody in particular
that are just, you know, radio silent
and no one knows what they're hacking on
and then they come to the event with,
you know, 40 criticals and you're like,
"Where were you Where where were you
hacking this whole this whole event?"
So, maybe that maybe that's a fun way to
try out. I don't know. I'm not I'm not
I know I've kind of got this uh
this
uh
uh reputation of being, you know, a a
full team collaborator, but I'm I'm open
to trying other other things and I might
I might do something new this year. So,
for this this upcoming year. So, we'll
see.
Yeah, I mean, it's really it's really
interesting to hear like both sides of
it. I think I think for Justin,
especially, it's a little bit different
because you do this like full-time for
your main income. Like this is your
full-time living and so the whole money
splitting aspect is a little bit
different and I think what I've found
over the years of doing collaboration is
one of the best ways you can do
collaboration just be explicit about
whether or not you're working together
on something. Like it's fine to work in
the same space and like bounce ideas off
each other or throw interesting things
in the chat, but if somebody like dives
into a hole,
like
you know, unless they're
Yeah, unless they're asking for help,
like yeah, you can maybe insert yourself
in there, but unless they're like kind
of like it's open-ended, like
you know, that's kind of their bug,
right? And then on the other side of it,
it's like you can ask. You can be like,
"Hey, do you want to dive in on this
together? Like this is pretty
interesting. Come take a look at this."
And like then you you know, I think
that's fair game for you guys to like
count that as like working together on
something. But otherwise, I think there
is still like that sense of
um
like working together. There's like a
whole concept of this for ADHD where I
think it's I forget what it's called
specifically, but it's like buddy like
working with a buddy. And just like
simply the the presence of someone else
doing work at the same time as you are
helps you be more productive because you
feel like you're like doing stuff
together and like there's more judgment
if you're like not on task and all that
kind of stuff. And so, that aspect of
literally just like being in a video
call, even if you're not working
together, I think adds a lot to the
productivity and the ability to like
work together and have those
collaboration moments, even if you're
not explicitly working together all the
time on everything.
Mhm.
Yeah, I I can totally I can totally see
that. And I I do want to
sort of plus one what you said about I
think it depends on your on your stage
of life and what your like how you treat
bug bounty. Like for me as somebody with
a with a full-time job, like bug bounty
money is kind of like Monopoly money at
this point. It just feels like prizes
and it's cool. Whereas if it was if it
was what I was buying my groceries with
or buying, you know, my
podcasting equipment with, then it would
feel
it would feel uh I would probably be
much more conscientious of how it was
how it was split and spent.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, and and because of
that, you know, when I when I've done
collabs in the past, I've been like,
"Hey, especially with hackers I respect
like Joel." I've been like, "Hey, you
know, I'd like to collab. I'd even
potentially be down to do a a full split
collab, um but we have to be putting in
similar time investments because if I'm
putting in 50, 60 hours a week and and,
you know, you're putting in 15 to 20
because you've got a full-time job,
right? And I'm not going to blame you
for not putting in 50, 60 hours a week
when you got a full-time job. Um you
know, then then that's going to not
that's not going to even out very well.
And so, I've always just kind of been
explicit with people and and and and I
do like the approach as well of like of
like having
Here I Here I am again bringing the
negative Nancy [__] up, but you know,
the like the chat where you like throw
interesting stuff in and stuff like
that. But but here's the problem with
that for me, right? Is that let's say I
find I find
a an endpoint and I fully exploit that
endpoint, right? And um and I I had like
maybe dropped it in the chat, but no
one's around and then they hadn't they
hadn't seen it. And then I go back and I
was like, "Oh, I you know, I fully
exploited it, right?" But then that time
somebody else somebody else on the team
had seen it. And and now I if I'm sort
of
you know, they say, "Okay, how'd that
go?" And I was like, "Oh, I popped it.
I'm good." You know, right? Now I've
sort of robbed them of the opportunity
to to exploit that endpoint had they
found it themselves, right? So, this
information trading thing is really
really really tricky, right?
Like like you said, you know, you don't
have to be
when you're doing this for fun, right?
Which some of us are even though it's
big dollars, you know,
it's not as intense, right? But when
you're doing this professionally and
you're, you know, a professional live
hacking event competitor, right? Then
these things get a little bit dicier.
So, I mean, what what do you guys think
about that? Do you think I'm being a
little too uptight about that or what?
No.
it's it's really case by case, right?
Like there are there are there are so
many case like edge cases that are
really difficult and I think just having
good communication in those moments and
just like being
like the conversation's not going to be
necessarily fun because it's like a kind
of about money and it's a little bit
sensitive and all that kind of stuff.
But I think just being upfront and
honest and like trying to meet in the
middle somewhere, like wherever it makes
sense, not necessarily in the middle,
but wherever it makes sense, then I
think that that's, you know, just going
with best intent.
Yeah. Yeah, what do you think, Douglas?
So, a bit a bit tangential, but one
thing that I have found that works
outside of the context of live events is
um so, is doing um like scope splitting.
So, to give you an example, a couple of
months back, um
I was in a
private
uh HackerOne challenge for the
Department of Defense uh with uh Rez0.
And I had been going really really hard
I got invited like a couple days before
he did. And I got I had been going
really hard on one particular
application um out of this out of the
entire scope. And he joins and we want
to collab together. And I'm like, "Look,
man, I already tore, you know, asset A
up entirely.
I'm happy to collab with you. You know,
you've already started working on asset
B. I'm happy to collaborate with you.
How about we
just you stay off of asset A. I'll stay
off of asset B cuz you're already
starting to go down that drain.
And then everything else we split."
Um and it it ended up working pretty
well. Like I felt like I was able to,
you know, tear up my
my scope item that I
that I had already gone very deep on and
I got to I got to know. And then he was
able to to do the same with kind of some
of some of his
everything else and it was very
lucrative for
uh for both of us. Um And that saves him
time, too, because he's not going and
duping at you on asset A, you know?
When we're not in the live hacking event
scene, the the collaboration thing is
very different because at the end of the
day, whoever submits the report gets the
gets the bounty, you know?
And so,
in the in those sort of situations, it's
it's a little bit easier. But the the
the the split the split scope thing I
think is
I think that's a that's a good shot and
I think it can definitely work in some
scenarios. Mhm. Yeah.
Cool. Okay.
That's collabing. I feel like we've
we've covered that. So, I did want
Hold on. No, no, no. You can't I just
pull me out.
I I I got I got questions for days. I I
know. I know. But, if I let you if I let
you keep going, we're going to spend an
hour talking about collabbing. So, we do
we do want to talk to to Douglas about a
couple other things. And one of those
things is this tweet thread that you
did. I think it was just March or May,
right? May of this year? Yeah, this was
great. Yeah, I think it was a few months
ago.
Yeah, yeah. It was called 100 very short
bug bounty rules. And it's basically
just a thread. I don't know if this was
a brain dump or if you had pre-planned
this. Maybe you could tell us a little
bit about how you came up with this.
But, I think it's a great concept. And
it was basically just like
a list of 100 things um that you should
sort of probably be doing when you're
doing bug bounty. And these are these
range from little tidbits of you should
use Burp Suite Pro to
um really in-depth stuff. Like, so what
why don't you walk us through a little
bit about what sort of spurred you to to
do this and what the process was like
and all that?
So, it's kind of a kind of a funny story
there. So, I
I'm a fan of of this uh this stoic
author Ryan Holiday. Been been reading
his stuff for for a few years. And he
had put out this like 100 very short,
you know, stoic rules for life. And it
was a it was a great thread. Um I like I
think I like liked it, retweeted it,
whatever.
Um
And then uh
Rez0 Joseph
decided like I guess he follows him as
well and then made some like
uh
like a mirror tweet. And it was like 10
very short bug bounty rules. And I was
so like frustrated that yeah, that he
only did 10. I'm like I'm like come come
on. If you're going to copy something
like as beautiful as this, it it needs
to be done like the right way. And so,
like out of spite, I was just like, "No,
I'm going to do 100 just to show you
that it can be done." And so, I think I
spent like I didn't use like ChatGPT or
anything. I just spent probably like 90
minutes uh in the like late afternoon
just like type it like typing them up as
fast as I could. I tried to I tried to
have a mix of like more like
philosophical behavioral like tips as
well as technical like technical tips
cuz not everyone wants just to have your
uh you know, don't stop trying or
uh if you're having a hard time, just
take a break. You know, that's kind of
that kind of gets dried and and
exhausting. Um
But, also you you know, coming up with
100 uh
uh
technical like bug bounty tips would be
extremely difficult. Uh also, my AirPods
are are going to die soon. So, I'm going
to switch to my MacBook speakers for my
MacBook. If if that's the if that's the
case, we can we can cut the audio and
reset it back up. But, I I really
enjoyed this this whole long tweet. And
I appreciate also that you did 100 of
them because like I don't know.
I'm not I haven't done much content
creating before I started this podcast.
And then I I've started doing some
content stuff since then. Um
it's freaking hard, my dude. It is very
challenging to like come up with all the
content and stuff like that you need to,
you know, to run a successful, you know,
to do a good tweet that that gets good
take off with the community and stuff
like that. So, I definitely appreciate
this. And and
but you know, I had a couple questions
about Sure. some of these that I and
that I wanted to kind of dive into,
okay? Yes, let's do it. All right. So,
number one,
starting off right at the very
beginning. It's a very good place to
start.
You say, "Spend at least 30 minutes on a
new target." Okay?
Um and then you say later later on,
"Give yourself a no bug time This is on
item number 15. Give yourself a no bug
time limit. I do 3 hours." So, um for
for me, I'm one of those people that it
takes me a little bit more time to start
finding bugs on a on an application
normally. Um so, I'm I'm wondering how
you reconcile these two and what that
first 30 minutes looks like versus the
the first 3 hours. Yep. Yes, so the
first 30 minutes I kind of go into this
with my now I'm sick talk. But, I
basically go assuming it's a SaaS
application, which is where I spend most
of my time. I go straight to user
management. And I look, "Okay, how many
different types of users are there? Is
there like just like two?" If if that's
the case, then there's probably not
going to be as many bugs that that sort
of fit my my flavor. Um or are there uh
uh you know, three custom roles where
you can like make a have like an entire
like matrix of okay, this user you can
give them this permission, but not this
permission. And then you can have an
admin role that has every single
permission except for this permission.
And then uh just like the more
complicated the the role structure, the
the more confident I'm going to be that
there's going to be bugs. So, first 30
minutes, go straight to user management
and especially like the the user invite
uh flow because that's where I find most
of my criticals.
Um and and higher higher security bugs.
Like, if I can if I can invite myself to
someone else's organization, okay, it's
like instant critical. If I can invite
myself uh if I can like invite myself as
another user, but who has higher
permissions, it's like, "Okay, that's
that's at least a high."
A lot of your a lot of your methodology,
and I believe I even saw it in that
tweet. But, a lot of your methodology is
built around uh this whole piece of user
auth matrices and like, you know,
organization and stuff like that. And I
think that's really good. And I think
that's awesome to have a bread and
butter like that. And certainly I I
think in the last life hacking I guess
the last one that I really participated
in
um in London, you know, I saw your some
of your brilliance with that, right?
With your the way you get the apps fully
configured and and the way you kind of
come up with these really crazy attack
scenarios. And I really appreciated
that. But, I'm wondering how you
approach
how you approach applications that don't
have this. So, in that first 30 minutes,
would you say if you came to an
application that doesn't have user roles
and stuff like that, are you moving
along to and checking all the other
targets before you come back?
Uh pro- probably. I think it it also
depends on how like complex the
application is. I think my other
sort of type of bug is um
like business logic errors. And so,
maybe it's an application where
uh there's going to be a lot lots of
bugs having to do with just bypassing
logic that the that's very unique to
that application. Maybe it's a
uh for example, I think you tweeted
about this not too long ago. Maybe it's
an application that has lots of like
levels of subscriptions. And so, that's
lots of opportunities for paywall
bypasses, right? Like, if if you can buy
if you can make a
like a business level subscription,
which gives you access to features ABC,
but then also an enterprise level uh
application, which gives you access to,
you know, features XYZ, then I try to
okay, as a as a free trial, can I get
access to business level? As a business
level, can I get access to enterprise
level features? Um
And then often times, if the program is
very good, every single feature that I
can that I can get access to is a is a
separate bug. Um especially if I can
find one that uh
where the paywall is actually enforced
because then I have evidence that um
that it wouldn't be a single fix. Like,
for example, if if I can uh
if as a business level user, I can't get
access to enterprise feature X, but I
can get access to enterprise features Y
and Z, it's like, "Okay,
uh Y and Z are going to be separate bugs
because if they're the same bug, then I
wouldn't be able to that I would should
also be able to get access to X, but I
can't." Yeah.
So, I Yeah, so like business logic and
um
or yeah yeah, business logic bugs are
kind of my second go-to after after user
uh authorization bugs.
Nice. That's really cool. So,
we I mean, I don't want to go through
like all of these. So, maybe this is a
good time to talk a little bit about
methodology since we're kind of already
on that on that route. So,
can you walk us through sort of how you
approach a new target? Cuz you're
always hacking. And like it I think it's
really impressive to see how quickly you
hop onto a program and are able to just
like find bugs and navigate it and get
it mapped out super quickly. So, how
what sort of what's your
approach? Like, what's your general
approach look like?
Yeah, so one of my one of my secrets is
that I actually spend a lot of time on
very small programs. Um I think it's
kind of there's a lot of hackers that go
after those really really big ones like
like Shopify or uh
or I'm trying to think of public
programs that I can talk about. Uh
PayPal um
GitHub.
Uh you know, these these large programs
that pay very large large criticals and
large mediums and large highs. Um but
I'll I'd say
maybe like over 50% of my bugs are on
programs that offer like $500 mediums
and $1,000 highs. And I just find I just
find a lot of them. And I kind of churn
through churn through smaller programs.
Every once in a while I'll find a a
really good program that's that's very
high paying. And I'll spend a long time
there. I mean, kind of become a an
anchor hacker there. Um but I've got a I
think I think if you look, I think
HackerOne has the ability to show you
your average bounty. And like my average
my average bounty is like only like
$700. Um and so, I I submit a lot of a
lot of $500 mediums and a lot of $1,000
highs. Um and so, and those are over the
like over a huge spread of uh programs.
You know, I'm not
like I I think I was talking to
to um cuz some hackers a while back and
they're like, "Yeah, I I've probably
submitted bugs to
you know, 30 or so different programs."
Like, I think I'm like close to like two
or 300 different programs that I've I've
submitted bugs to. Wow. Yeah, just a
lot. Because I just I just spend time on
the on the small ones. And I just kind
of like churn through those.
I submit one or two and uh and move on.
So, maybe I'm
maybe I'm taking the the quick and easy
route. But, it's uh it's been working
well.
Wow.
Super interesting. That's that's really
cool. So, I guess
that you know, with moving so quickly,
you know, you've got this this 3-hour
time limit. You get to the end of that 3
hours. Let's say you haven't found
anything. Is that a a stop for you
normally or Usually, and I'd say 3 hours
and and in my tweet I said I said 3
hours
in my in my tweet I said 3 hours. If
it's a smaller program and a smaller
scope it's not going to be 3 hours. Like
you know, if it's a WordPress site I'm
not going to spend 3 hours trying to
break WordPress site.
Yeah. Um
But like on the most complicated
application, yeah, if I get to if I get
to 3 hours I I should I should backtrack
and say outside of the context of a live
event where I'm being paid and asked to
spend you know, spend time on one
particular program. It's like okay, if
if I get to 3 hours and I haven't found
anything I'm usually not going to to
find something unless I
you know, put in another like 10 at that
point I finally might be able to start
finding things. But like I said I I go
through I go through a lot of a lot of
small programs and so if I haven't found
anything after 3 hours, you know, I'd
rather move on to a smaller program
where I can find something in
you know, an hour. Um and it just kind
of
keeps me motivated. That that's that's
absolutely crazy to me then. Like I
spend so much more time on on an actual
like target before I move along if I
don't I probably will spend 20 hours may
maybe three four hacking sessions on a
target without finding a bug if I if I
think this is a high value target. But I
guess I will say I do typically go for
the programs with the higher payouts
though. So that's really impressive to
me that you're able to find bugs that
you know, in that 3 hours. And Joel, I
mean do you I mean where where do you
lie in that in that I'm curious. Well, I
was I was going to ask
two questions about that. So for me I'm
like kind of in the middle on that where
I'll spend a decent amount of time
hacking and I try to identify attack
surface and decide sort of as I'm going
whether or not this attack surface is
something that I want to spend a ton of
time on because if it's something that
seems small like I don't know.
If I'm seeing if I'm hacking something
and it's just one GraphQL API endpoint
and it's not particularly large GraphQL
and
I start poking at it and I don't see any
real red flags. Yeah, I'm sure there's
probably some bugs hidden in there, but
I'm not sure how much more time I'm
going to go spend on that program if I
see that they have systemic security
measures that aren't like yeah, they
they I'm sure there are again areas
where it's not you know, perfectly
airtight, but that is not necessary like
if I want to make a you know, farm a
program or something like and I see
something that's secured I'm not going
to
spend a bunch more time on that cuz I
want to make some money. I want to
optimize my time there.
Yeah.
I was curious if you spend you know,
whatever your time limit on a program
and then you find nothing and you hit
your no bug limit, what comes next? You
you know, say you've been hacking for
you know, you just started. You spent 3
hours. Okay, you've been going for 3
hours you found nothing. You just hit
your no bug limit. What do you do for
the rest of the day? Do you just stop
hacking or what what do you have like a
backup plan?
Uh yeah, I mean usually if if it's in
one day usually I'll stop. I'm I I rare
outside of the context of a live event
where I'm you know, basically treating
bug bounty as a full-time job.
Um I'll I'll stop for the day. I can't I
can't hack for more than 3 hours in in
one day. Um
unless I happen to start like in the
morning and then I
have some time like
7 hours later in the evening. Um I'm not
going He's making a face like I can't
hack for less than 3 hours.
Are you Are you freaking kidding me
right now, dude? Like you telling me
that you never you very rarely hack for
longer than 3-hour contiguous periods?
Yeah, that's Yeah, that's pretty
god. How do you even do that? Oh my god.
My eyes hurt, man.
Dude, this guy's a beast. This guy is an
absolute beast. I I could never I would
never find anything.
Uh okay. So the other thing I wanted to
ask was
like you mentioned that except for like
for live hacking events like you
normally have like a no bug bug limit
and then you stop hacking or move on or
whatever. Uh what does that look like
for a live hacking event in terms of
success rate? Do you find that it's
better to spend the time and just keep
pushing on that target even if you pass
your no bug limit or
do you find better success?
Uh also
I yes, in a live hacking event I think
that they the targets are much much
deeper
um and the payouts are much much higher
than my
typical 3K credit programs. And so yeah,
I'll I'll spend I'll spend a lot more
time. Like for example, if it's uh
um you know, like there was an event in
Austin last year and it was um
uh it was on it was GitHub, you know,
and it took me like 3 hours just to get
GitHub Enterprise Server set up. It's
like okay, so
Yeah.
And so
So I'm going to I'm going to spend more
time in the context of a live hacking
event where there's much higher payouts
and much deeper
complex applications. Um but live
hacking events are are only a small
portion of the year. And so the rest of
the year I'm just trying to maximize my
time like you were talking about Joel
and just kind of
turn through turn through programs and
and find the
find the best uh
time for money uh
uh balance.
Wow.
That's that's really cool. I I
definitely have not done very much
program churning and I've got like you
know, 500 freaking invites sitting there
that I I need to you know, that I've
never even looked at. So I feel like
maybe I should should go through and
just you know, hit them real fast. Maybe
even bring it down to like you know,
well actually I mean you got it you said
30 minutes even for the first initial
assessment. So maybe I'll I'll hit them
30 minutes 30 minutes 30 minutes 30
minutes and see if they've got some
interesting features and especially when
you know, you've got those programs that
are like
like 5K credits, you know, or like you
know, 6K or 7K, you know, those are not
your big you know, 40K credits or or
whatever from some of these other
programs, but but they still like are
pretty good, you know, and so I think
there's definitely some some
you know, really
good monetary opportunity for those
programs especially for someone like me
who's a full-time full-time hunter.
Um
Okay, so let's go back to the tweet. Uh
next one that I wanted to talk about and
this kind of ties in was the match and
replace rules. Uh
you say quote 13, use match and replace
rules to find new endpoints. Now I use
match and replace rules for lots of
things. I think a lot of the top hackers
do. Um and I'm wondering how I'm
interested by the fact that you said to
find new endpoints. So could you tell me
exactly how that works for you? Sure,
yeah. So I am kind of a dummy and don't
know how to use
to find new endpoints. Like I don't I
don't know how that works. And so
so to think I have to have the
application find endpoints for me. And
so I'll notice in the responses to a lot
of requests usually like when I load a
like the application initially it will
like the like you'll see like get user
slash user user info will be like is
admin false in that like the JSON
response. I'm like okay, something on
the JavaScript side cuz I don't
understand JavaScript at all is using
that that uh response body to populate
the populate the page. And so I'll just
you know, make a match and replace rule
that's like is admin true. I think there
was like one application a while back
that had like
like 15 different booleans different
roles. Um
and I was like I just like added them
all. Like is is what true? Is blank
true? Is blank true? Um
and it made the you know, the UI
disgusting a mess, but it gave me access
to different parts of of the application
that I would be able to find if I knew
how to actually read JavaScript. So
that's kind of
that's kind of what I do.
Dude, that was that was my follow-up
question cuz I wanted to know like
dude that end dude are do you are you
doing like a lot of static analysis and
that kind of stuff to also find the
endpoints? Cuz I like that approach that
you mentioned that's like why would I
find the endpoints when I could let the
application find the endpoints? And I
think that is definitely the case a lot
of the time with JavaScript where often
times the bundles for other pages or
hidden hidden stuff that you wouldn't
normally be seeing or you might not know
it's there is still getting pulled down
by the client and you can see a lot of
that if you if you you know, dive into
it and take a little bit of a closer
look.
But it it sounds like you're pretty much
just like
you know, let the application actually
show me it. He's just raw dogging the
match and replace right there.
I'm sure I'm sure I would I'm sure I'll
find more bugs when I eventually get
around to learning how to how to hack,
but um Yeah.
So that that that's cool though and I
think for any any of any of the people
out there that are listening that don't
know how to assess JavaScript files, you
know,
uh Douglas is at every live hacking
event and he does great and he's very
much a valued member of this community
and so he's up at the top and he has got
there even without knowing how to find
endpoints in JavaScript files, which for
to me to be honest is like kind of
crazy. Like that is such a core part of
my methodology and also something that I
teach at a very early stage to new
hackers. Um so the fact that you've done
this well without ever doing that is
like there's some sort of secret sauce
in there that I need you know, and maybe
it's just the match and replace, but
either way it's it's very impressive,
man.
Um Yeah, I'm like I'm like a bow hunter
who who knows that I could you know,
hunt further with a with a rifle, but I
just never never learned how to use one.
That's awesome. Um so one of the ones
you mentioned we'll go a little bit out
of order here, but number 76 says that
if the app uses Intercom which
Intercom is like the little support
bubble like chat chat with us thing in
the bottom right, right? Um
then you say try booting it with another
email.
that mean? What is that Is that like for
account confusion stuff?
Yeah. Yeah, so so Intercom is really
interesting in that there This this
concept called identity verification and
they even write an entire article on how
to do it. But the thing is that
Intercom widgets are typically set up by
sales teams and they might not be the
most technical and or they might just be
lazy. And so so what happens often is
I'd say maybe like 20% of the time you
just see the Intercom widget and what
you can do is just open up your your
console in the browser and just type
like Intercom open print boot and then
email and then give it some other email
and then enter
and it will basically start up the
Intercom widget as if you were logged in
as
as the user with that email. So I'll
usually try like email test@test.com and
usually there's been some salesperson
that's
registered on the application with
test@test.com and you'll be able to see
their see their their chats that they've
had.
In fact Wow, super interesting. Yeah, so
I wrote a blog about this
and there was a
because there was a hacker one there's a
third-party
hacker one vendor that um
that did just this and basically as a
result I was able to
uh
view like social security information of
any hacker because
because I could I could log into any
other hackers
account on this third-party
using the Intercom widget and then their
password reset functionality was just
like resetting it to something like
winter 22 bang or something. What? Yeah,
so they they'd give you like a hardcoded
temp password and be like hey I'm Ryan
Rader
I want to know where he lives. I want to
know his you know his social security
number and then be like okay No. Here's
your password.
Wow. Oh my gosh.
Crazy. Yeah. I I I missed somehow I
thought I went through all of the things
on your blog but I somehow I missed this
dude and I'm looking at it right now.
This is from 2021. November 3rd is when
he released it and this is hilarious.
You've got you're like
it literally says they respond back and
say use the temporary password
summer@123.
No. Yeah.
Wow.
Yeah. Yeah, which by the way your blog
is is awesome dday.us. Yeah.
Yeah, there's so many really uh
really cool blog posts there. Yep.
That's awesome. We'll definitely we'll
definitely link those. Um that's one
that I've never heard of and I'm
definitely going to be on the lookout
for it because Intercom is everywhere.
Yep. Um so Yeah. I'm kicking myself
right now because I can't even imagine
how many of those I've you know slid
straight by without ever talking about
it. Just just earlier today I found a
a random application that I was hacking
on and it was using Intercom. They they
were they were secure they were using
identity verification but yeah and so
probably like
maybe 10 to 20% of the time you'll
you'll just be able to boot into someone
else's chats and see their
see their chats. I've probably made
about like $10,000 with that bug over
the course of the
over the course of the last couple
years. Yeah.
Wow.
That's crazy man. I I know you said that
most of them were really like original
tips that were like new ideas.
Uh
Some of these were like definitely more
like
you buy it on a sign at HomeGoods.
Yeah.
It's like be thankful for failure.
Okay, no no no dude okay hold up Joel.
That that one's a great one and I I put
that on there for a reason because No,
it's great. It's great. I'm just
It was either that or live laugh love. I
couldn't Exactly. Live laugh love. No,
you need like we need like you know
HomeGoods bug bounty edition, right?
Yeah. Yeah.
No, I thought this was really good one
though because I
this is something that I talk about all
the time which is like if you're
especially if you're getting into bug
bounty or you're training in bug bounty
you should be thankful for those those
those fails. You know you're getting out
there and I think this is also very
similar to the other one which is um
30 number 30 on your list which is pin
your success on whether you followed
your plan not if you found bugs, right?
So I think those go together really well
and and that you know even if you're if
you're if you're saying all right I'm
going to test these this features this
asset
and so on and so forth. If you're able
to focus on that even if you're failing
you're getting your reps in you're
you're figuring out what attack vectors
don't work you're getting your you're
training your intuition for this target
and you're getting closer and closer and
closer to the to the next to the next
bug, right? I mean is that was that what
you had in mind when you wrote these?
Exactly. Exactly. Because like you you
know you think like okay I'm hacking on
a on a on a program for during live
hacking event.
I put in the reps I tested you know X
asset for 5 hours like there are other
hackers that are going to also be
testing that same asset for 5 hours and
finding and finding nothing. And so you
finding you know you spending the time
and not finding anything is just getting
that out of the way just like everybody
else is going to. Exactly.
Yeah, this reminds me a lot of
a thread you did Justin
a couple months ago about I think it was
about a Human Lab episode Yeah. that was
talking about motivation and why like
you shouldn't reward yourself or you
shouldn't like discipline yourself if
you fail basically even if you're
holding to your plan like and you don't
find anything for example, right? Bug
bounty is not paid for effort it's paid
for results
which is something that we say a lot
like all the time. Yeah. The reality is
that if you spend a bunch of time and
you find nothing don't discipline
yourself and be like oh god I'm so bad
at hacking cuz you didn't find anything
because it's not paid for effort it's
paid for results and just cuz you didn't
find anything doesn't mean that you're a
bad hacker. Like you learned a lot from
from that time just like the time with
the the scope and looking at the target
and learning new things like there it's
still very very valuable. Mhm. Yeah, I
think this is especially true when
you're when you're learning but it it's
even it's even true when you're more
experienced as well because every app is
different, right? And and so all of us
are just learning these apps that we're
we're going into hack.
So I think I think that's that's some
good some good sage wisdom from from bug
bounty Uncle Douglas Day here.
And then the next one can actually go on
a on a on a little poster which is there
is no end enjoy the journey. Talk to me
a little bit about that one.
Give me your thoughts on that one. Yeah,
so I think like it it was it was really
easy
it was really fun
um
starting bug bounty because I didn't
have necessarily some end goal that I
was going after. I was just like I'm
trying to figure out figure this out.
Maybe I'll eventually get to go to a
live hacking event and then I think as
soon as There's the middle report.
4 hours later I
got to talk about about my first report
of this episode.
But
but but no I mean it's there's there's
always going to be bugs you're always
going to be hacking there's not like
there's there's no finish line and so I
think you'll just start to get depressed
if you still feel like you're X number
of bugs away from a finish line you just
kind of got to just keep going cuz it
it's not going to stop until until you
do. I mean eventually I'll get to a
point where I'm like okay I've I've done
enough and I'll and I'll hang up the
keyboard and you know sit on my porch
with a shotgun on my lap or something.
I'm at least
a couple months away from that point so.
Nice nice. Well
Go ahead Joel. Yeah, why don't you talk
a little bit about that cuz that sounds
like more of the like peaceful life the
life side of like away from keyboards.
So how do you how do you do that
balance? You mentioned that you only
hack like 3 hours a day
and all that kind of stuff. I imagine
part of that is cuz you have a family
obviously and there's you know family
responsibilities and obligations and all
that kind of stuff. How do you do that
balance of the back and forth.
Oh goodness this is the question.
So I remember hitting my sort of
meteoric rise in bug bounty right around
the time I started getting invited to
lots of hacking events.
And
getting basically on the live event
train 2 years after starting bug bounty
was
it was awesome financially but it also
created a really like weird expectation
in my mind that in order for me to have
a hobby it had to be income generating
and Dude, yeah. And so if like I could I
felt like I couldn't justify doing
anything I couldn't justify hanging out
with friends cuz I'm like man if I I
could do bug bounty and I could make you
know X number of thousands of dollars or
I could hang with hang out with my
friends and make $0. So maybe kind of
shoot it feels like hanging out with my
buddy is costing me you know $2,000
because I'm not finding a critical
tonight and good Dude, that's that's a
very profound way of saying it actually
like I had not ever put it into words
but like I don't know why I got so
addicted to to it you know and I was
like man why why am I not pursuing other
hobbies and I came you know came to the
same conclusion a different way but to
hear you say it's costing me $2,000 to
hang out with my friends. That's
opportunity cost. Yep. That's that's
deep man.
Yeah, yeah and so you end up just kind
of like being a a shadow version of
yourself where you're not able to
justify doing anything that isn't
isn't productive and you kind of get
like hooked on this uh
on this productivity
grind set and yeah I I went through a a
very long time where I was just not able
to enjoy
enjoy life
um
and uh
yeah I mean I don't know what to say
other than you just you have to have
something that you do that's that's for
fun and in try to like I try to frame it
like that it's kind of like the
the engine oil to my my car that is
myself.
It's like yeah engine oil isn't going to
run the isn't going to run or isn't
going to get me from point A to point B,
just like hanging out with friends and
playing board games isn't going to make
me money, but it's also going to make
sure that my car doesn't break so that
it can get from point A to point B. And
it's, you know, having having a social
life and having hobbies is going to make
sure that I don't, you know, break down
and just uh Yeah. not
uh and lose all motivation to to hack.
So, Well, the the the listeners here
know how how I am with analogies, but
I'm going to I'm going to take an
attempt here to take this little bit
further. And and you can even No, no,
let let just hold on. Just just just
bear with me.
him cook. Let him cook. All right. Okay.
Um you know, you said that this is the
oil, right? Hanging out with friends is
the oil. And then, you know, you're in
the car. But the the point of the car is
to get you to the destination, right?
And I think we can even we can even talk
about this in in a bigger picture, which
is all of this, I guess, it it it it's
to a destination of, you know, or you
could say money in general or earning in
general is to this destination of
creating this lifestyle that you want or
this lifestyle that you need to to do
your live your life and and, you know,
it could be generosity, it could be, you
know, getting the new hot tub you want
to sit in, it could be this or that,
whatever our goals are. Um you know,
those are also keeping those in line and
not getting caught up in the little
metrics of like, all right, did I make,
you know, X tens of thousands of dollars
in bug bounty this month? Um that's
something that I found really hard to
keep in my in my, you know, sight over
the past couple years of doing bug
bounty. Right. Yeah, cuz like no matter
no matter how much you enjoy the work
that you're doing, you can't work just
to enjoy the time that you're not
working. Like I think I think like work
is is very holy. And so, do having
working for the sake of doing like the
work itself and do, you know, hacking
because you enjoy it and enjoying the
actual hacking process and having that
be its own ends is is really important.
Otherwise, like I mean, yeah, I really
enjoy hacking, but if the only reason
I'm hacking is so that I can
afford a new hot tub and
and better enjoy the time that I'm not
hacking, then it's like, what's what's
the point? Um so, I think there has to
be a
a really good uh
I guess what am I trying to say? I think
that there is
work work itself, I think, is a needs to
be a
a core part of the life, right? Enjoying
it. It's Are you talking about almost
going back to your journey sort of thing
here? You need to enjoy that journey
along the way, right? Yeah. Yeah. And it
needs it can't be just a means to an
end, I think.
I mean, doing bug bounty needs to be
something you enjoy. And I I think I've
I've I've mentored a number of people in
bug bounty and
it it's been kind of clear that their
reason for doing it, you know, they see
the they see the money that I've made at
the live event and they're like, "Oh,
shoot, I really, you know, want some
money to be able to do whatever." And
it's like, you might be able to do that
for a short while, but if you don't
enjoy if you're not like interested in
in security and you don't like enjoy
that puzzle aspect of of bug bounty,
then you're just doing this for the
money and it's not going to it's not
going to last and it's not going to
stick. Whereas, if you're doing it
because you're curious and curious and
you really enjoy the
the the process itself, then then yeah,
it'll it'll uh
it'll be a lot more sustainable.
Solid, man. Yeah, no, that that's that's
that's very key, I think, for people to
understand in the bug bounty scene. Um
you can't We always say on the pod as
well and I give I I give this to advice
to people that are trying to get into
bug bounty. You can't be doing bug
bounty just for the just for the money
of it a lot of the time, you know,
if you do, there's going to be a lot of
things you're going to run up against
that you're not going to know how to
deal with. So, at the end of the day, it
really really helps um for you And and I
guess let me let me restate that. You
can, uh but there there will be
difficulties that will not be there if
you if you don't also love if you also
love bug bounty. That that's the way
that it goes a lot smoother. Um I I see
this extend also into like way more than
just bug bounty. I mean, this is true
for every single industry. There are so
many
flashy industries that really draw your
attention in that want you to like that
make people, you know, drop everything
they're doing and go switch industries
to go chase that crazy thing. And like
sometimes that works out, but there are
a lot of cases where just simply chasing
it might get you some money in the short
term, but it's not really going to be
something that you enjoy doing. And if
you find something that can do both of
those things, which bug bounty can be
that beautiful intersection for a lot of
us, then
then that's an awesome thing to do. But
it's not for everybody. And like that's
why there are tons of people who do
purely app sec and no bug bounty. And
also people who do tons of bug bounty
and no app sec, right? And there's like
so many sides of the spectrum that it
just needs to be like something that you
enjoy doing and and genuinely
um are having fun with and that like,
you know, actually satisfies you.
Otherwise, it's just going to turn into
that that grind where you start to dread
it and it's just like not fun anymore.
And yeah.
And I think that's where the the hacker
or not the hacker necessarily the hacker
one, but the the bug bounty community in
general kind of comes into play because
I think that bug bounty like the bug
bounty community is
uh
uh the bug bounty community is what
makes bug bounty enjoyable for me. It's
not just not just the hacking, it's
hanging out with with people that I've
become friends with. Like I
um hanging out with
uh with hackers like like you guys,
being on Twitter, being, you know,
doofuses, uh responding to like Like I
think uh whenever uh the hacker Like he
always says, like you guys, hanging out
on Twitter, being doofuses. Being
doofuses. I mean, that's pretty much all
we do.
Well,
so there's there's kind of like a a game
that I play I like to play with uh with
Pure Luke where uh Ben, you know,
NahamSec will post like a Twitter or a a
new YouTube episode and he's always got
some like facial expression uh in in the
thumbnail. And then so, like Pure Luke
and and me will always just like, you
know, imitate him and like post it in
the Twitter thread. And I mean,
all like
dumb things like that to make bug bounty
fun cuz you feel like you're you feel
like you're in a in a tribe.
Yeah. Yeah, and and you are and it and
it is a lovely experience. And there's
all so much lovey-dovey and touchy-feely
feelings for the bug bounty community,
but here on Critical Thinking, we talk
about the technical details. Yep. So,
let me let me let me let me get let me
rope it back in. I have a couple things
before we run out of time that I want to
I want to pick your brain on. Yep. Um
and so,
one of the things that I
uh one of those things is this whole
concept of
auth Z testing,
you know, creating matrices and stuff
like that. So,
I've seen you go so far as to, you know,
build out a little, you know, either a
spreadsheet or or you know, write it
down of how you're testing various roles
and permissions and stuff like that. So,
could you talk a little bit about that
functionality?
Yeah, yeah. That uh that part of your
methodology. So, this is something that
that will like is very slow and it's not
very exciting and it's not very fun, but
in the context of a of a live event
where I need to go deep and I need to
test for bugs that ever that other
people aren't testing for,
yeah, I'll go I'll go so far as to take
a list of the roles,
um make a make a matrix of them like and
then each kind of like type of
functionality. So, I'll have like admin,
uh
not quite admin, but still high-level
user, um read-only user, and like anon.
And then I'll have like uh
inviting users to your org, uh
writing documents, creating reports,
viewing reports, etc. And I'll have a
list of like every piece of
functionality and then just kind of like
go and try to
try to figure out what is the
what user should be able to do what and
then find
cases where user
you know, A might be able to do function
X even though according to the
documentation, they're they're not. And
so, reading the like reading the docs
like a really really good documentation
will have this matrix built out for you.
Um and I I love it when I when I
encounter that. And then you can kind of
just go, "Okay, according to the docs,
you you slap right there a report like
like ammunition. You're like, "According
to the docs, this user shouldn't be able
to do this. I can do this.
There's my bug."
Um and like they they can't they can't
say that it's not a bug. I mean,
occasionally you'll feel like
I love I love this part of Douglas. He's
like, "And it's in the docs. And because
of that, it's definitely a bug and you
can't argue with me." It's true. Like
occasionally occasionally you'll see
someone who's like, "Oh, the docs team
is is are outdated docs." And then
they're like, "I got to like leave the
program."
Now, put it in the docs. Documentation
issue. Mur mur mur mur mur. I know. I
know. But being able to like come like
stack with like ammunition so that the
program can't like weasel their way out
of of uh of uh of a bounty saying it's
like intended functionality. It's like,
"No, it can't be intended functionality
because it's in the docs. And I've read
the docs and I know you haven't." Do you
Do you Do you have like a specific
technology that you use to document
this? Or do you actually physically
write it down? Or do you Does it vary
from time to time? Or what? It's usually
just like a a Google spreadsheet. Um
like a So, like a sheet Google Sheets.
Joel's Joel's eyes just got Did
Did someone say
Google spreadsheet?
I'm going to check on my custom Notion
page.
Yeah, I mean, do you do you color code
stuff? Do you Do you just, you know, No.
No, because it I mean, I run into I I
run into
over there dying. He's like, "I'm sorry,
what? Not color coded? Like what?" Yeah,
I run into these situations Just give me
a link. I'll come in and fix it.
Um
but yeah, it's uh
yeah, our back benchers saying it's it's
really helpful when you're when you
really need to go deep and you need uh
to to find to find bugs because I mean
these things can't be fixed
systematically or programmatically. It's
like
they
all these endpoints, they need to be
properly scoped and oftentimes,
especially when new roles are added over
time,
um it's going to be a real developer
pain to have to Yeah. try to scope every
single one of these endpoints. Um
I think one of my like one of my highest
paid programs is a very small like 3K
crit program, $500 mediums. And I've
submitted I think like 100 different
like reports on this one program. I
think
I've made like 60K or on this on this
program.
That's nuts.
$500 $500 bugs.
Yeah. Yeah, it's just a tons and tons
and tons of them and just it's
it's just going through each of these
endpoints and finding
uh where where this uh
you know, where users are be able to
call endpoints that they shouldn't be
able to call. And it really helps in
this particular program. It lets you
build custom roles. And so you not only
is it like that you have the you know
like three or four given roles. It's
like I can make a role that has this
permission and this permission but not
this permission. Mhm.
And so that's uh it's usually you see it
like
sure that gets super complicated, you
know, once once you have
the ability to make custom roles and
stuff like that. Whatever spreadsheet
you're you're using gets probably crazy
looking. Yep. Yep. Exactly. And what's
what's really fun is when the the
program like fixes it with like a V2 API
but doesn't turn off the V1 API. Oh my
gosh. No. And then she's like, "Hey, you
can still do this by using the the V1
API." And then you know,
ah
I'm I'm curious if you feel like does it
ever feel like gamifying the system or
like
um how often do you find that report or
that programs will close like if you
submit one report per endpoint or
something? How often will they close
that all as one fix? It's it's a good
question. So kind of going back to how I
I go through I churn through a lot of
small programs. Um one one thing one of
my strategies or methodologies is I'll
put out like little canary reports or
like dealer reports where I'll submit
like two reports to a brand
So important.
to a brand new program and just see see
how they're handled. So for example, I
got invited to a a program like about a
month ago. Um it was a pretty like
looked like a pretty good program, not
too many too much activity, a pretty big
application. Uh went and found um like
two like decently impactful idols um
on on the app um within my you know,
three hour window and
submitted them and I'm still uh I think
I submitted them 28 days ago and I'm
still
still waiting for the bounty and uh
yeah, I'm like, "Okay. So
It's not a good sign. It was it was easy
to it was easy to find the bugs but I'm
not sure I want to wait, you know, a
month to get to get to get paid. So I
just kind of
you know, like even though there's
probably bugs to be able to uh to find,
I'm I'm probably not going to come and
swing around uh to find more bugs there.
Mhm. Yeah. That makes sense. And and so
I guess going back to the the
methodology piece,
there's and and we actually kind of
talked about this a little bit before
because there will be an episode coming
out eventually. It's in our it's in our
emergency episode, you know, sort of
backlog of like if for some reason we
can't record one week, then we'll we'll
send out this video. But essentially uh
I wanted to talk about this this concept
of nose in the application that you talk
about in your NahamSec talk. I loved
this when I saw it. It really resonated
with me and it really um I think sets up
a good framework for how to identify
vulnerabilities in an application. Um so
could you talk a little bit about that?
Yeah, so this this is my kind of like
one of my favorite things um because
when I I've taught a lot of people or
maybe like
five to 10 people how to how to bug
bounty hunt.
And the most common reaction I get is,
"Wait, that's a that's a bug?" Cuz I
think when people I think about bug
bounty hunting, they're thinking about
like
authentication bypasses like being able
to like log like log in as any user.
They're thinking about RCEs or uh SQL
injections or squillies as I call them.
Um
Oh oh no. Oh god.
You don't you don't know what squilly?
No.
Get off the podcast. Yeah, so
Just leave right now. I like this guy.
That he had to say that. He had to say
squillies. Like oh jeez. Squillies.
Yeah, so uh
But no, I'll be like
I'll be finding these these bugs.
They're like, "Yeah, this this read-only
user can
perform some action that that does a a
write."
Um and they'll be like, "But who cares?"
And I'm like, "But I care and the
program cares because they they
specifically set this trust boundary and
we are breaching that trust boundary."
And they're like,
"But that's that's a security bug?" And
I'm like, "Yeah, like if if I as a as an
application don't want some user to be
doing something. If I'm telling them no,
you can't write, you can only read, then
any any time that user can write, that's
a that's a security vulnerability." And
so just thinking with that mindset of
where is the application
where where has the application been
designed and configured to not let me do
something. And every single one of those
is an opportunity for a bug. Nice. And
that's kind of just how I how I approach
really any application.
So
um
Yeah. That those those
having those sort of frameworks, I think
for me my methodology has sort of
uh evolved over the years in a very
intuitive sort of way. Like and as I as
I'm kind of coming into the content
creation scene, I'm trying to figure out
how do I put these into frameworks. And
I love it when you get a nice, simple,
clean framework like what you just
described to help you identify stuff.
Just open open the app, look for the
nose. Look for the places where you
should be, you know, where where the
application is telling you you can't do
something. Look for it in the
documentation. Look for it in the grayed
out buttons. Look for it, you know, all
over the place, right? And uh and take
those and and try to try to exploit
those. I really like that and and I
think uh
I think sometimes those those sort sort
of bugs can get um
I guess
like you mentioned, they're not the the
squillies.
They're they're not the RCEs but they do
have a lot of impact time sometimes and
sometimes they're just a violation of
the trust boundary and that's something
that the that the team wants to clean
up. And at the end of the day, it's not
our responsibility necessarily to define
what threat model a company has. It's
it's our responsibility to find the bugs
that violate the company's threat model.
Um and so that's what we do. Yep.
Exactly. I think that's a really good
way of like mapping out like the the
threat model. Mhm. Uh which is like a
really difficult thing to do. We've
talked about this a bunch where it's
super difficult both from the program
side and the hacker side to from the
hacker side to identify what the threat
model is supposed to be and from the
from the security team side to explain
what how how the security team is
approaching the threat model when a bug
comes in. And so I think you can sort of
find those hard stops essentially where
like, "Oh, in the documentation it says
this." Or in the app it does a certain
thing. Or there are these certain
limitations that are in place that tell
me
this is where the threat model is. This
is the barrier. You get around this,
then this is something that's hard like
hard to find. Exactly. And I like what
Justin said about grayed out buttons.
That's kind of another another big
telltale sign, especially when you can
just like right click, inspect element
and then turn you know, enable it. Boom.
Yeah. Bug. Yeah. Nice. I love that,
dude.
The classic.
Yeah, so so one more thing that I wanted
to talk about before we wrap it up and
that is the sort of mapping your hacking
sessions blog post that you put out in
2021.
I really like this. Once again, it's a
good it's a good framework. It's a good
practice for bug bounty hunting. Tell us
a little bit about that and how that's
affected your your bug bounty hunting.
Yeah, this is this is approach I I
typically go I go with after I've taken
a fair bit of time off of hacking or if
maybe after I've just come off of a long
hacking event where I'm I come off and
then I'm not sure what to hack on and
that kind of that decision paralysis of
ah
I have so many options available. I've
got like hundreds of private programs,
hundreds of public programs.
I don't I don't know what to hack on.
And then I
like the cost of context switching is
just so high in bug bounty cuz you're
like it is, man. You could you could
spend you know, half an hour on you
know, program A and then like the entire
time you're hacking on program A, you're
like, "Oh man, is my is my time better
spent over on program B? Am I just like
wasting wasting time here? I don't
know."
Target B or you know, scope item B, you
know. Exactly. And then you end up just
kind of like second-guessing yourself
and then maybe like you give up too like
too early and you're like, "Okay, I'm
actually going to hack on you know,
program B or uh asset B." Whereas you
know, if you would have only if you
would have spent you know, like 15
minutes on on asset A, you would have
found a bug. And so Mhm. just creating
like the the concept of mapping your
hacking is just creating a rule like a
predefined rule when you're in a clear
space uh like clear mind where you're
like, "Okay, I'm going to spend one hour
hacking on GitHub and I'm going to
you know, I'm going to try to mess with
the the GitHub CLI and see if I can't
modify issues that I don't have access
to."
Mhm.
And then af- after that one hour or two
hours or what- whatever it is, that's
you've already given yourself permission
to switch to switch scope. And the
decision the decision's already been
made for you and so you don't have that
hanging over your head the entire time
you're hacking. And so really I guess
the the essence of that methodology is
just pre
it's just making the decisions
beforehand when you're in a
in a clear and um
not stressed out uh state of mind.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's that's
that view. I mean that's like the best
way to make failure like failure case
things so that you're basically ready
for failure. Like a lot of people will
start to to shift the goalpost over time
when they hit failure. They'll be like,
"Okay, well, let me just give it 2 more
hours." Or let me
keep keep going until I find at least
one thing or whatever. And that that'll
just like keep going.
Yeah, but but like I think that's like a
really common trope to fall into. And if
instead, like you said, like if you set
those hard deadlines and you
plan ahead of time, "Okay, if I fail in
this amount of time, then I'm I'm
setting guardrails for myself so that I
I don't just keep shifting the goalpost.
Like I go and I do something else." And
it's not just like a constant like you
fail harder and harder. Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. And you can feel good. Like
even if you didn't find any bugs, you
can be like, "I executed the plan. And
next
you next time I'm going to set, you
know, I'm going to map it this way and
then I'm going to execute again." And
then I mean we've we've
we've done bug bounty, you know, all of
us here have done bug bounty long enough
that we we all know the bugs are there.
There's never like it's never a case of
there aren't bugs to find. There are
always bugs to find. It's just a matter
of going until you find them.
And
you just keep mapping your hacking
session, you'll have
and you keep executing on the plan, then
you'll have success after success after
success. And then eventually the success
will also include a bug.
So, you I think one of your superpowers
as a hacker is your consistency and your
I guess disciplinedness,
you know, with these frameworks and with
these ways to approach targets and these
rules. And and I I really like what you
mentioned just a second ago when you're
haven't been hacking for a little while
and you've got this sort of like restart
anxiety, right?
Going into it. It's very real and you've
got a plan to you've got a you know, a
counter plan to to get over it. Um
I'm I I want to ask though,
how often do you follow your own advice
here? How often do you do this? Give me
give me a rough percentage of times when
you actually do what you are talking
about. Um
I'd say most of the time during in these
situations where I have scheduled my
hacking. If there are many many many
times where I'll just be like in the
middle of like
you know, doing some other thing that
isn't hacking and a brand new program
and bug will come and it's just like
boom boom boom rush rush rush rush rush.
You know, that those rules that I set
don't really apply there because it's
about you know, it's exciting. I've kind
of like
I'm brought into it without or I'm
brought into a hacking mindset without
uh
without having time to like map my
hacking. I'm just like it's a brand new
program. Let's give it a shot.
Similar similarly with um
with uh
can't think of like other situations.
Um
maybe
someone will like come like someone will
ping me and they'll be like, "Hey, you
know, Douglas, can you
can you look at this?" Or
I'm in a couple of Discord groups where
we'll just all collectively decide, "Oh,
we're going to all hack on hack on, you
know, program X." Like, "Okay, I'm not
going to make everyone stop so that we
can, you know, schedule out and and map
our our hacking session. We're just
going to hack against it." But during
the during the moments
or the times of the week where I'm like,
"I'm going to hack from, you know, 8:00
p.m. until 10:00 p.m." Or I'm going to
hack until, you know, from Saturday
morning at
9:00 a.m. until noon.
Those like scheduled hacking hacking
times are where I I will follow my own
advice.
Wow. That's that's pretty that's pretty
crazy, man, that that on a regular cuz
like even when I have scheduled hacking
time,
I I think sometimes I just sit down and
I just kind of play around with stuff,
you know? And and and maybe that's
that's inefficient, but um you know,
yeah, that that's pretty impressive to
hear that that most of the times when
you're actually sitting down
intentionally hacking, right?
That you're actually getting that that
done. Yeah. And I'm not perfect, but I
think a lot of it has to do with I I
have less like I have a family and I
have less free time to hack than than
the average
like bachelor or bachelorette. Yeah,
average
no kids full-time bounty hunter. Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. So it's like, "Okay, my
my you know, Tuesday evening from 8:00
p.m. until 10:00 p.m. and my Saturday
morning from 8:00 a.m. until noon." Like
those are like my hacking hours. Those
you know, those like six
those like my six hours of that week
that I get to have solid hacking time. I
want to be able to like capitalize and
maximize on those. And and I also know
that they're coming ahead of time. So
it's not and so it's it's it's easier to
to be more disciplined when it's a very
limited amount of time and I know ahead
of time when it's happening.
Very cool, man. Very nice. Well, that
that is the that is the summary of all
of the technique related questions I
have for you.
We are getting pretty far along in time.
Joel, did you have anything else you
wanted to add in before we close up?
I I I think we've exhausted everything
except for Douglas's social security
number from him. So Yeah, exactly.
Which maybe we can get with an Intercom
bug. Yeah, like like let's see. Boot
Intercom bug.
Yeah. No, that's great. All right, man.
Well, thanks for coming on the pod. It's
been a pleasure having you on and and
it's you know, like you said, it's a
it's a pleasure always hanging out with
you at the live hacking events and being
part of the community together. So yeah,
I appreciate you making time for it.
Yeah, it's been real. Appreciate you
guys having me on and
as always I'm I'm looking forward to to
listening to the podcast.
I did I did have I did have one other
question. I know you I know you guys
don't call SQL SQLies, but do you do at
least call RCEs Rickies, right? Oh my
good All right, that's it. Cut it. Cut
it. Cut it now.